A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015
The Library of Virginia
51854
XX
LVA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 51854, transferred on 28 June 2016.
Historical Information
The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the General Assembly passed at the May 1779 session and has continued to the present day. Its antecedent was the General Court, which, after it was reestablished under the constitution of 1776, shared appellate jurisdiction with the Supreme Court until 1851, when the new state constitution abolished the General Court. Prior to that date the General Court had criminal jurisdiction, while the Supreme Court was restricted to civil cases. While the court now has concurrent original jurisdiction in issuing and hearing writs of habeas corpus, mandamus and prohibition, retirement, removal, and matters of judicial censure, its jurisdiction is almost exclusively appellate. An act of the General Assembly passed on March 16, 1971 changed the name of the court to the Supreme Court of Virginia.
Justices are elected by a majority vote of both houses of the General Assembly for a term of twelve years. Vacancies on the court occuring between sessions of the General Assembly may be filled by the Governor for a term expiring thirty days after the commencement of the next session of the General Assembly. By statute, the Chief Justice is chosen by a majority vote of the seven justices.
By statute, the court by designate a retired justice to serve as Senior Justice for a renewable one year term. Senior Justices sit with the court during regular sessions hearing writs and sitting on merit cases, especially when an active member of the court is recused from hearing a particular case.
The Court of Appeals of Virginia was established on January 1, 1985. It provides appellate review of final decisions of ghe circuit courts in domestic relations matters, appeals from decisions of an administrative agency, traffic infractions and criminal cases, except where a sentence of death has been imposed. It also hears appeals of final decisions of the Virginia Workers' Compensation Commission. Except in those cases where the decision of the Court of Appeals is final, any party aggrrieved by a decision of the Court of Appeals may petition the Supreme Court for an appeal. The Court of Appeals consists of eleven judges. The court sits in panels of at least three judges, and the membership of the panels is rotated. The court sits at such locations as the chief judge designates, so as to provide convenient access to the various geographic areas of the Commonwealth.
Biographical information related to individuals documented in this collection (in alphabetical order):
Judge Rosemarie Annunziata (b. 1940) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1995-2005, and as a senior judge on the court from 2005 to 2015. She was a circuit court judge in Fairfax County from 1989 to 1995.
Judge James W. Benton, Jr. (b. 1944) was appointed to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1985 and retired in 2007. A native of Norfolk, Benton attended public schools there and participated in civil rights demonstrations while he was in high school. He earned an undergraduate degree from Temple University and a law degree from the University of Virginia. He worked for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund in Richmond and was a partner at the Richmond law firm of Hill, Tucker Marsh.
Justice Harry Lee Carrico (1916-1913) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1961 and was Chief Justice from 1981-2003. He took senior status in 2003. Before joining the court, he was a lawyer and judge in Fairfax County. Carrico was born in Washington, D.C. and reared in rural Fauquier and Fairfax counties. He was an ensign in the Navy during World War II.
Justice George Cochran (1912-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1969 to 1987. A life long resident of Staunton, he was a member of the House of Delegates from 1948 to 1966 and the Virginia Senate from 1966 to 1968.
Judge Samuel W. Coleman (b. 1940) served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 1985-2001. He has served as a senior (retired) judge from 2001-2010 and 2013 to present. Coleman was born in Kingsport, TN, and grew up in Gate City, VA, where he attended public schools. He earned an undergraduate degree from the University of Virginia and a law degree from Washington and Lee University. He practiced law in Gate City until he was elected circuit court judge in the Thirteenth Circuit (Lee, Scott, and Wise Counties). In 1985, Coleman was elected to the first Court of Appeals of Virginia.
Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr. (b. 1944) was appointed to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 2002 and he retired in 2014. He served as chief judge from 2006 to 2014. A native of Suffolk, Felton attended public schools there, and college and law school at the University of Richmond. He practiced law in Suffolk, taught law at the College of William and Mary, and worked in the Office of the Attorney General and the office of Governor James S. Gilmore before he was appointed to the court.
Judge Johanna L. Fitzpatrick (b. 1946) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1992 to 2006. A native of Birmingham, Alabama, she attended Tufts University and earned a law degree from Catholic University. She began working for the Fairfax Legal Aid Society in 1974. In 1980 she was elected judge of the Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court in Fairfax County, making her the second woman elected judge in Virginia. In 1982, Fitzpatrick was elected circuit court judge in Fairfax County.
Judge Robert P. Frank (b. 1944) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2005 to 2012, when he took senior status. He was born and raised in Newport News, Virginia. He earned his undergraduate and law degrees from the University of Virginia and then practiced law with his brother in Newport News from 1968 to 1986, when he was elected judge of the Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court, Seventh Judicial Circuit in Newport News.
Judge James W. Haley, Jr. (b. 1942) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2005-2012, when he took senior status. He was born in Washington, DC and was raised in Arlington, Virginia. Haley attended Washington and Lee University and the University of Virginia School of Law. He was a law clerk for Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia John W. Eggleston, 1967-1968, and then worked as an assistant commonwealth's attorney in Arlington County. He practiced law in Fredericksburg and was County Attorney for King George County. In 1985, he was elected general district judge in the Fifteenth Judicial Circuit, and in 1989 because a circuit court judge in the same ciruit. He was elected to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 2005.
Judge William H. Hodges (b. 1929) served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985-1989. He was a state delegate, 1962-1966, and a state senator, 1966-1972, when he was elected as a circuit court judge. He practiced law in Norfolk and Chesapeake from 1960-1972. He continued to serve as a substitute judge after he retired in 1989.
Justice Barbara Milano Keenan (b. 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1991 to 2010, when was confirmed as a judge on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Previously she was a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from 1985 to 1991. She was the first woman to serve as a circuit and appellate court judge in Virginia.
Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr. (b. 1940) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1995 to 2011, when he took senior status. He was one of ten judges who served on the first Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1985 and served on that court until 1995. He was the second chief judge of the court, serving from 1985 to 1993. From 1976 to 1984, Koontz was a circuit court judge in the 23rd judicial circuit in Roanoke; from 1968 to 1976, he was a juvenile and domestic relations judge in the general distict court in Roanoke.
Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy (b. 1945) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1989 to 2007, when she took senior status. She was the first woman to serve on the court, the first woman to serve as Deputy Attorney General in Virginia, and the first woman to as a judge on the State Corporation Commission. Lacy was born in South Carolina and grew up in Wisconsin. She worked in Texas as as an Assistant Attorney General and Division Chief (1972-1976) before moving to Virginia. She was Virginia Deputy Attorney General overseeing civil litigation (1982-1985) and Judge, State Corporation Commission (1985-1989).
Justice Charles S. Russell (b. 1926) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1981. He returned to the court as a senior justice in 2004. Russell practiced law in Arlington and Fairfax from 1951 to 1967, and was appointed judge for the 17th Judicial District in 1967. From 1967 to 1982 Russell was a circuit court judge in Fairfax County. Russell was born in Richmond, Virginia, and served in the U.S. Navy in World War I and in the Korean War.
Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997, when he took senior status. A lifelong resident of Covington, Va., Stephenson practiced law there and was Alleghany County Commonwealth's Attorney and a judge on the 25th judicial circuit befor his appointment to the Supreme Court.
Justice John Charles Thomas (b. 1950) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1983 to 1989. A native of Norfolk, Thomas graduated from the University of Virginia law school in 1975 and worked at Hunton and Williams law firm in Richmond, where he became the first African American to be named partner in a law firm in the South. When Thomas resigned from the Supreme Court in 1989, he returned to private practice at Hunton and Williams.
Justice W. Carrington (William Carrington) Thompson (1915-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1980 to 1983. A native of Chatham, Virginia, he attended law school at the University of Virginia and established a law practice in Chatham after returning from service in the Navy during World War II. Thompson served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1959 to 1968 and the Virginia Senate from 1968 to 1973. He was a circuit judge before his appointment to the Supreme Court.
Justice Henry H. Whiting (b. 1923) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1987 to 1995, when he took senior status. Whiting was born in Fort Logan, Colorado, and spent most of his youth in Winchester, Virginia. He atteneded Virginia Tech for one year before enlisting in the U.S. Army during World War II. After the war, he attended the University of Virginia and earned a law degree in 1949. He practices law in Winchester for much of his career. In 1980 Whiting was appointed to the 28th Judicial Circuit by Governor John Dalton; in 1987 he was elected by the General Assembly to the Supreme Court of Virginia.
Scope and Content
These recording include Supreme Court of Virginia and Court of Appeals of Virginia audio and video recordings of court ceremonies and oral history interviews, 1969-2015.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies, 1991-2011
Series II.
Series III. Audio recordings of court ceremonies, 1969-2005
Contents List
- Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies,, 1991-2011., Extent: 23 video recordings.
  This series contains 23 video recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1991-2011. Includes investitures and swearing-in ceremonies, portrait presentation ceremonies, as well as retirement and anniversary ceremonies. The ceremonies took place in the courtroom in Richmond unless otherwise noted.
  Includes the following ceremonies:
  Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Courtroom 5-E, Fairfax Judicial Center in Fairfax, Virginia, 1991 July 2. Includes one video recording of the entire ceremony with poor audio (43 minutes) and two segments of the television show Law Weekly (60 minutes), a production of the Fairfax County Bar Association, moderated by Glenn C. Lewis, with highlights of the ceremony and interviews with guests. The segments were broadcast on the Fairfax County public access television station, FCAC Channel 10. The ceremony was the first televised session of the Supreme Court. Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; with remarks by Raymond Diaz, president of the Virginia State Bar; William D. Dolan, III, past president of the Virginia State Bar; Governor L. Douglas Wilder; Speaker of the House A. L. Philpott; State Senator Edward M. Holland; State Senator Richard L. Saslow; Retired Judge Arthur W. Sinclair; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Johanna Fitzpatrick; and Justice Keenan. The second segment of the recording features host Glenn Lewis interviewing guests Emilie Miller, Virginia State Senator; Fairfax County Commonwealth's Attorney Robert H. Horan; Chief Justice Carrico; Virginia Court of Appeals Judge Charles H. Duff; William Dolan, Raymond Diaz, Judge Sinclair, Judge Richard T. Horan, Justice Keenan, Ann Milano, retired Clerk Delores Testerman, Judith Wheat, and Jerry Phillips.
  Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Olin Hall, Roanoke College, Salem, Virginia, 1995 August 16 (49 minutes and 30 seconds). Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by George W. Wooten; Judge Beverly T. Fitzpatrick; Michael Smith, president of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate C. Richard Cranwell; and Justice Koontz. Invocation and benediction by Rev. R. Paul Hendrickson, Chaplain, Roanoke College. The recording also includes clips of local television news coverage of the event (WDBJ News 7 and WSLS News 10).
  Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, Lee High School, Jonesville, Virginia, 1997 July 8 (1 hour, 32 minutes). Chief Justice Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor George Allen; Senior Judge Glenn Williams, U.S. District Court, Western District of Virginia; Justice Kinser, and others. The recording includes footage before and after the ceremony and the following reception. Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997. She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2010. She is the first woman to serve as chief justice.
  Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 2003 January 1 (43 minutes, 18 seconds). Poor quality video recording. Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary; and Justice Donald W. Lemons; presentation of slideshow with photographs of family and court staff.
  Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (36 minutes, 41 seconds). Justice Barbara Milano Keenan, presiding; invocation and benediction by George Martin; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Speaker of the House of Delegates, William Howell; Bernard DiMuro, president of the Virginia State Bar; Colonel George B. Mason, Jr., Virginia Capitol Police; Justice Keenan; and Chief Justice Hassell. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 265 Virginia Reports, vii-xviii. Produced by Craig Keeton, Community Idea Stations, Richmond, Va. Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011. He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007. He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.
  Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 February 11 (45 seconds). Justice Barbara M. Keenan administering the oath of office, with Chief Justice Hassell's wife, Linda Hassell, holding the Bible. Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr. (1955-2011) was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989 and served until his death in 2011. He was elected to a four-year term as Chief Justice in 2003 and reelected in 2007. He was the first African American to serve as Chief Justice.
  Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, recorded at Roanoke College in Salem, Va., 2003 March 5 (1 hour, 5 minutes, and 35 seconds). Chief Justice Hassel, presiding; remarks by State Senator Charles Hawkins, Delegate Robert McDonnell, Attorney General Jerry Kilgore, Delegate Lacy Putney, and Justice Agee. G. Steven Agee served on the Supreme Court of Appeals from 2003-2008, when he was appointed to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Previously, he was judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2001-2003.
  Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 June 1 (47 minutes). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Senior Justice Harry L. Carrico; U.S. District Court Judge John A. Gibney; Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; Trish Harrington, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia; Robert N. Baldwin, Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia; and David Beach. (Video in two parts) David Beach was Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1984-2003.
  Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2004 December 9 (41 minutes, 48 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., presiding; invocation by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Mark Warner; Lt. Governor Timothy Kaine; Attorney General Jerry Kilgore; Senator Kenneth Stolle, Chair, Court of Justice Committee; Speaker of the House J. Morgan Griffith; David B. Bobzien, President of the Virginia State Bar; and Chief Justice Hassell.
  Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2005 March 24 (1 hour, 11 minutes, 51 seconds). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; remarks by Bill Howell, Speaker of the House; Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna Fitzpatrick; James Ullman, former chair, House Courts Committee; Retired Judge J.R. Zepkin, Judge Phillip Trompeter, and Larry Palmer, Clerk, Lynchburg Circuit Court. (Video in two parts) Robert N. Baldwin was Executive Secretary for the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1976-2005
  Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell, 2006 February 28 (28 minutes, 8 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix-xii. Harry L. Carrico (1916-2013) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1961 to 2003 and was Chief Justice from 1981 to 2003. A. Christian Compton (1929-2006) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1975 to 2000. Charles Russell served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1982 to 1991, and returned as a senior justice in 2004. Roscoe B. Stephenson (1922-2011) served on the Supreme Court of Virginia from 1981 to 1997.
  Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution, 2006 November 2 (46 minutes, 35 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, presiding; remarks by Lt. Governor William Bolling; Attorney General Robert F. McDonnell; Speaker of the House William Howell; President of the Senate John H. Chichester; Senator Benjamin Lambert; Karen A. Gould, President of the Virginia State Bar; Governor Tim Kaine; and Chief Justice Hassell.
  Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2007 October 10 (12 minutes, 48 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy, R. Hassell, Sr., administering the oath of office to Goodwyn, who is accompanied by his wife, Sharon Smith Goodwyn, and his two children. Brief remarks by Chief Justice Hassell, and greetings from Senior Justices Elizabeth Lacy and Charles Russell; Executive Secretary Karl Hade; and Patricia Harrington, Clerk.
  Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 February 22, Manassas, Virginia. (Length?). Chief Judge William S. Fenton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Paul B. Ebert, Prince William County Commonwealth's Attorney; Senator Charles Colgan (presenting commission); William G. Petty, Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia; Robert J. Zelnick; John D. McGaven; and Justice Millette. LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008. He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.
  Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette, Jr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2008 September 5 (2 hours, 7 minutes). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Delegate Robert G. Marshall; remarks by Senator Henry L. Marsh, III; Manuel A. Capsalis, President of the Virginia State Bar; Delegate Jackson H. Miller; Delegate Jennifer L. McClellan; Governor Timothy M. Kaine; Senator Charles J. Colgan; and Justice Millette. Benediction by Delegate Ward L. Armstrong. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 276 Virginia Reports, xi-xxii. LeRoy Francis Millette, Jr., served on the Court of Appeals of Virginia from February 2008 to August 2008. He was sworn in as a justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia on August 19, 2008.
  Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 November 17 (48 minutes, 21 seconds). Chief Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr., presiding; remarks by Senator Henry Marsh; First Lady Anne B. Holton; Governor Tim Kaine; Chief Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr.; and Judge Powell. Cleo Elaine Powell was the first African-American woman appointed to an appellate court in Virginia.
  Investiture of William C. Mims as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2010 April 9 (1 hour, 10 minutes). Chief Justice Hassell, presiding; invocation by Stephen R. McCullough; remarks by Senator Thomas K. Norment, Jr.; Senator Richard L. Saslaw; Mark E. Rubin; Jon D. Huddleston, on behalf of the statwide bar associations from Virginia; Speaker William J. Howell; Govenor Robert F. McDonnell; Courney M. Malveaux; Judge Dean S. Worcester; Justice Mims; and Attorney General Mark L. Earley. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 279 Virginia Reports, xxv-xivi. William C. Mims was elected to the Supreme Court of Virginia on March 10, 2010. Previously he was Chief Deputy Attorney General under Attorney General Robert McDonnell, and Attorney General following McDonnell's resignation to campaign for Governor.
  Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 February 16 (47 minutes). Justice Donald W. Lemons, presiding; remarks by Governor Robert F. McDonnell; Senior Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy; and Chief Justice Kinser. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 281 Virginia Reports, xi-xxiv. Cynthia Dinah Fannon Kinser was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1997. She was elected chief justice August 31, 2010, effective February 10, 2011. She was the first woman to serve as chief justice.
  Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 September 1 (46 minutes, 28 seconds). Chief Justice Cynthia Kinser, presiding; invocation by Reverend Betty C. Reiff; remarks by Retired Chief Judge of the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, Johanna L. Fitzpatrick; Senator William C. Wampler, Jr.; Delegate Terry G. Kilgore; Governor Robert F. McDonnell; former Attorney General Jerry W. Kilgore; Hon. Joseph P. Johnson, Jr.; benediction by Reverend Walter P. Weikel. Elizabeth A. McClanahan was appointed to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 2011. She was a judge on the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia from 2003 to 2011.